<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Joes Blog</title><link href="http://joe.marrama.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://joe.marrama.com/feeds/Travel.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://joe.marrama.com/</id><updated>2013-02-09T23:59:00-08:00</updated><entry><title>Hooligans and Curry</title><link href="http://joe.marrama.com/hooligan_battle.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-02-09T23:59:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Joe Marrama</name></author><id>tag:joe.marrama.com,2013-02-09:hooligan_battle.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Our first activity of the day was going to the Oxford-Bristol soccer game. We
were warned before that both teams are 5-th or 6th level teams (as opposed to
1st level, like Man. U. or Arsenal, etc) and are therefore shitty, and also
that no one in Oxford besides hardcore local fans really cares about Oxford
football. Despite these warnings, we couldn't be prepared for the magnitude of
the cultural experience we were about to get. We take the bus there and are
instantly greeted by hundreds of police officers lined up along the trail. I'm
used to police presence at sporting events, but have never seen this many for
such a small game. We immediately head to the beer tent outside of the stadium.
The tent contains a couple of counters selling beer and cheap burgers, and the
whole place is packed with fans. Once we grab beers we stand outside of the
main crowd, who begin chanting loudly and in completely unintelligible accents.
According to Connor, they were first chanting about Oxford's and Bristol's
hatred of a mutual rival, and then the Bristol fans switched to chanting about
their own team. It was hilarious listening to a bunch of drunk fans chant
nonsensical things, but eventually the volatile combination of alcohol and
rabid rival soccer fans turned sour (who would've thought?). About 20 minutes
from our arrival, a fight breaks out in the middle of the crowd. The cops
quickly run over and break up the fight and surrounding crowd, which has a few
effects. It (hopefully) broke up the main fight, but it also turned the crowd
up a notch in anger and it dispersed everyone else who wanted to fight all
around the parking lot. While this might not have been the ideal outcome, the
cops were absolutely obligated to come in and break up the main mob before
people started to get seriously hurt. Anyways, things start to get a bit more
intense. Once the cops dispersed the main mob, we slowly tried to make our way
to the stadium, but fights kept breaking out all around us. We stood only a few
meters away from some, watching drunk British men seriously try and beat the
crap out of each other with nothing held back. The standout fight happened as we
were trying to edge around a grassy knoll. Two rival groups of about 5 people
each saw each other from opposite sides of the knoll and immediately charged
each other. Connor's friend summed it up perfectly when he said it looked like
"a shitty version of braveheart". They met each other with drunken ferocity I'd
never seen. I still vividly remember one guy knocking another over onto his
knees and then kicking him square in the face. After seeing this outbreak, we
started to walk with a little more purpose towards the stadium. Fortunately,
seating is segregated in the stadium, making it the safest place to be in a few
mile radius.   &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="image"&gt;
&lt;img src="./static/images/travel/riot_police_small.jpg" width="600"/&gt;
&lt;div class="caption"&gt;The police barricade after the game&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we were warned, the actual game was horrible. The level of soccer was
noticeably lower than any game you'd ever see on tv. The first half mostly
consisted of each team booting the ball back and forth, with occasional passing
and moments of real soccer. It wasn't that pretty to watch, but at the very
least the crowd provided great entertainment. Highlights included a drunk old
guy behind us calling a player a "fat cunt" at the top of his lungs, two
younger teenage fans calling every player "shit" in a scathing tone with thick
accents, and the constant yelling between the two extremely well barricaded
sections. The other team won by a PK and a sloppy breakaway goal, and we left
before the rival team's fans started to leave. Leaving the stadium, there was a
row of about 100 police officers barricading the rival fans from oxford fans,
which provided much-needed separation and a great photo op. We promptly left on
the next bus to town and went back to Tom's house to reflect on the experience. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After getting a couple drinks in us, we went to curry with the bros and the
lads. "Getting curry" is a popular activity in Oxford, exclusively because all
of the curry restaurants are BYOB. As you might imagine, this attracts tons of
college students. We got there around 8:30 or so, which was just late enough to
be seated next to 2 loud tables full of drunk college students making speeches
and drinking. We got some curry, did more drinking, and eventually became those
obnoxious college students, making speeches and all. Tom ordered a fancy dish
that came out sizzling, and one of the lads said "happy birthday" jokingly to
Tom. We thought nothing of it, but after dinner was done a waiter brought out a
complementary birthday cake for Tom, so we had to give fake birthday speeches
about Tomas. I froze up in the middle of mine, Hannah and Jimmy made friendly
and praising speeches, and all of the lads' speeches were (predictably) filled
with healthy amounts of sarcasm and insults. Connor went last, and decided it
more appropriate to punch the cake instead of actually making a speech. It was
awesome. After eating some disfigured cake, we went to a couple more pubs and
then headed back to bed.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Oxford"></category></entry><entry><title>Sachsenhausen and the Labyrinth</title><link href="http://joe.marrama.com/berlin_labyrinth.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-01-26T23:59:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Joe Marrama</name></author><id>tag:joe.marrama.com,2013-01-26:berlin_labyrinth.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We started the day moving apartments from our first Berlin AirBnB stay to our
second Berlin AirBnB stay (booked after mass confusion and panic), which was
fortunately only a block down the street. After dropping off our stuff at the
new place, we quickly left for our tour of Sachsenhausen, the closest
concentration camp to Berlin. Our tourguide was a very tall, skinny, and pale
Brit named Rob, who was very quick-witted and clearly experienced at giving
tours. We met up with our group of about 15, took a train for 40 minutes, a bus
for another 5, and then finally began our tour at Sachsenhausen around 12. Much
like the tour of Yad Vashem, witnessing the horrors of Sachsenhausen eventually
gave way to an enveloping sense of numbness. One of the first major topics we
covered was the SS and their methods for keeping the camp under control with
only ~300 officers for ~50,000 prisoners. They obviously had fences, guns, and
machine gun turrets surrounding and overlooking the entirety of the camp, but
this wasn't enough. To really control the prisoners, they employed an ingenious
and cruel system of hierarchy and intimidation, primarily designed to break the
prisoners spirits and turn them against each other. When a group of prisoners
arrived to Sachsenhausen, the SS would pick one prisoner that stood out from
the rest and beat him to near death infront of the rest of the group. The
prisoners would then be sorted into a rigid hierarchy, with criminals occupying
the highest position, jews occupying the lowest, and blacks/roma/other
undesirables occupying everything in between. This helped to turn the prisoners
against themselves, further helping prevent an uprising. Over and over
throughout the tour, I found myself involuntarily muttering expletives. The
sheer cruelty and evil that they institutionalized is beyond description.
Learning about all the gritty details of how they carried out this evil really
drove home how horrible they were. To carry out everything that SS soldiers did
required a special combination of brainwashing (to see others as subhuman),
cruelty, evil, and blind unquestioning obedience to authority. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="image"&gt;
&lt;img src="./static/images/travel/IMG_3334.JPG" width="800" /&gt;
&lt;div class="caption"&gt;Entering the camp. The monolithic figure in the
center is the russian memorial&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="image"&gt;
&lt;img src="./static/images/travel/IMG_3344.JPG" width="800" /&gt;
&lt;div class="caption"&gt;Jewish prisoners' sleeping quarters&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The worst part of Sachsenhausen was the area specifically reserved for
mass murdering. They only employed gas chambers and shooting people into pits
on a minor scale. The main method with which they murdered over 10,000 russian
prisoners of war and other undesirables at Sachsenhausen was called the
"neckshot" method. This was where they had incoming prisoners go into a
"medical examination" room one at a time, stand behind a height-measuring
device with a slit down the middle, and then the executioner would shoot the
person in the neck from the other side of the slit. This solved a major
problem, which was the psychological toll that having to execute someone
face-to-face was taking on SS officers. Once the prisoner was executed, his
body would then be incinerated. During the war, the only visible sign of
industrial murder outside of the death-building was the copious amount of smoke
produced by constant cremation.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="image"&gt;
&lt;img src="./static/images/travel/IMG_3346.JPG" width="800" /&gt;
&lt;div class="caption"&gt;Memorial next to the neckshot room&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We finished up the tour, walked back to the train station, and bid Rob
adieu. After we got back to our new place, we grabbed dinner across the street
at a little cafe recommended by Grace. It didn't disappoint, although we
unfortunately left ourselves a small amount of time to experience "the
labyrinth". Recommended by our friend Adrienne, "the labyrinth" refers to
Salon–Zur wilden Renate, a small bar/club in Berlin that houses a crawling maze
in the back. I insisted on going as our last activity in Berlin - I trusted
Adrienne's wisdom and didn't want to miss out. We rushed on public transit and
got there exactly at 10, which is when they stop accepting people in the maze.
Out of sheer luck, the hostess included us as the last 2 people in the night's
queue of labyrinth-goers. The door lady said it would be two hours before we
could go in, giving us plenty of time for a few drinks. We bought a couple of
cheap and strong mixed drinks and grabbed seats in the little venue-area to
watch this weird electro-punk band that was playing. I was instantly convinced
that this was the weirdest show of my life. The band, Sado Opera, was made up
of a DJ-keyboardist duo in the back, a drummer on an electric drum set, a
skinny lead singer, two backup lady singers, and a dwarf. They warmed up by
playing the two same songs over and over again to check levels and coordinate
the light show. The first song was a catchy song about 'fire at the disco', or
something like that. The second song was an equally catchy song that is
described well by its line: 'I dream of love but I make fuck with
every-every-everybody'. The chorus consisted of the 2 lady backup singers
yelling "I'm so sad - I'm so lonely - Just a squirt - Make me squirt" in a
hilariously German voice. They also spent a little time coordinating the lights
for a special part of their show. The lead singer instructed the light tech to
flicker the lights when he (the lead singer) did the following actions: yelling
"THERE IS HIGH VOLTAGE", writhing around on stage, and pretending to clamp
alligator clips on the (topless) backup singers' nipples. Throughout their
warm-up set, Hannah and I were cracking up. I couldn't believe how weirdly
awesome and awesomely weird this band was, and that we were getting to
experience it all! Regrettably, the band was actually playing their real set at
3:30am, and considering we had an 8:45am train to catch, this was a bit out of
the question. On our way out, we got to meet them and they enthusiastically
handed us their card and told us to like them on facebook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Midnight came around quickly (time flies when you're having fun) and
shortly thereafter came our turn for the Labyrinth. Hannah went in first, and
they led me in a few minutes after. The lady put a blindfold over my eyes and
led me by hand into the start of Labyrinth, where she took the blindfold off
and closed the door. The Labyrinth itself was basically a big adult
playstructure with tunnels and enclosed spaces and weird artwork all over the
walls. There was a room with a bunch of monstrous vaginas painted on the wall
whose exit itself was a big vagina, and there was a room/tunnel containing a
bunch of interesting artwork made out of old metal car parts and stuff. I was
running through like a kid in a candy shop, trying to take it all in and
capture the most exciting parts on my phone's camera. I had a bit of a buzz
before entering, but I was riding a purely natural high of excitement all
throughout the maze. It was the best thing I could've hoped for to end our trip
to Berlin. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="image"&gt;
&lt;img src="./static/images/travel/IMG_0567.JPG" width="500" /&gt;
&lt;div class="caption"&gt;Vagina door inside the Labyrinth&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="image"&gt;
&lt;img src="./static/images/travel/IMG_0570.JPG" width="500" /&gt;
&lt;div class="caption"&gt;A mini diorama at the end of a crawlspace&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="image"&gt;
&lt;img src="./static/images/travel/IMG_0574.JPG" width="500" /&gt;
&lt;div class="caption"&gt;What lies beyond?&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="Berlin"></category></entry><entry><title>Masada and the Dead Sea</title><link href="http://joe.marrama.com/masada_dead_sea.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-01-14T23:59:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Joe Marrama</name></author><id>tag:joe.marrama.com,2013-01-14:masada_dead_sea.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This day began bright and early at 7, when Hillel picked us up from our AirBnB
outhouse in Jerusalem. We promptly set out for Masada, an ancient ruin
overlooking the Dead sea that was once held by Jews and conquered by the Romans
in 73 or 74 AD. Before we got there, we made brief stops at the sea level
marker (the dead sea is 423 meters below sea level) and a little gas station
market. When we got there we bought tickets and prepared for our walk up the
front of the mountain that Masada resides upon. We took the "snake" path up the
mountain, which derives its name from its numerous switchbacks. I decided to
get some exercise by power walking up the path, and in the process took off my
shirt and sweat a lot. Right after I got to the top, a tram-load of old
tourists happened to come up at the same time, all of whom took great delight
in laughing at me, calling me 'Americano', and taking pictures. I was too tired
and hot to do anything but laugh back at them; it was probably a hilarious
scene to have observed. After waiting for Hillel and Hannah to make their way
up, we began a thorough tour of the ruins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="image"&gt;
&lt;img src="./static/images/travel/IMG_2861.JPG" width="800" /&gt;
&lt;div class="caption"&gt;Looking up the front of Masada. You can barely
see the snake path winding up towards the tram station&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="image"&gt;
&lt;img src="./static/images/travel/IMG_2862.JPG" width="500" /&gt;
&lt;div class="caption"&gt;Canyon to the south of Masada. Everything
surrounding Masada looks like this&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the more salient points that Hillel made was that the beauty of
Masada lays in the life that its Jewish inhabitants maintained before their
end, not in their tragic end itself. The (compacted) story of Masada is that it
was made into a fortified hideout by the paranoid roman king Herod, captured by
Jewish rebels in 66 AD, and then largely destroyed by a roman siege around 73
AD. When the Jewish rebels realized their eventual defeat upon running out of
ammunition, they decided to commit mass suicide instead of submit to capture
and enslavement by the Romans. While the story of Masada is very powerful, I
tend to agree with Hillel. Life in ancient Masada was surprisingly rich and
comfortable, for living in the middle of a desert 2,000 years ago. The
facilities built straight into the mountain for bathing, food storage, defense,
and most impressively water collection were absolutely fascinating and
ingenious. I couldn't believe that the Romans were able to create a fully
functional city housing thousands of soldiers on top of a mountain in a desert.
Solely utilizing technology from over 2,000 years ago, Masada's inhabitants
could store years worth of food, have a steady stream of water, and even have
the luxury of hot baths. Also, the Jewish rebels converted the roman horse
stables into a synagogue. To honor the spirit of Masada, the synagogue is still
used. I'm not sure how much its actually used or what its used for (its quite
small), but when we visited it we saw a rabbi inside making copies of the
torah. Masada was definitely a high point of the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="image"&gt;
&lt;img src="./static/images/travel/IMG_2863.JPG" width="800" /&gt;
&lt;div class="caption"&gt;Remains of original paint in a room on Masada.
The black line denotes where the original remains meet a restoration&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="image"&gt;
&lt;img src="./static/images/travel/IMG_2867.JPG" width="800" /&gt;
&lt;div class="caption"&gt;Looking down from the top of Masada. The two
rockpile squares are where the Romans led their siege from&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="image"&gt;
&lt;img src="./static/images/travel/IMG_2875.JPG" width="800" /&gt;
&lt;div class="caption"&gt;A restoration of the hot baths in Masada. Hot
water comes from the bright cave in the top of the frame and disperses into steam beneath
the floor supported by small pillars&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="image"&gt;
&lt;img src="./static/images/travel/IMG_2889.JPG" width="800" /&gt;
&lt;div class="caption"&gt;Standing in king Herrod's chambers&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="image"&gt;
&lt;img src="./static/images/travel/IMG_2893.JPG" width="800" /&gt;
&lt;div class="caption"&gt;An exhibit showing how Masada got its water. It
flowed in through the small aqueducts on the side of the mountain, and then was
carried up a path to Masada by donkeys.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="image"&gt;
&lt;img src="./static/images/travel/IMG_2894.JPG" width="500" /&gt;
&lt;div class="caption"&gt;A rabbi inside the old synagogue copying a torah.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our next stop was Ein Gedi, which is a little area north of Masada that
has pretty vegetation and a stream running through it. Like Masada, Ein Gedi is
surrounded by barren desert. We went for a short walk up the stream and I swam
around in a cold pool around the base of a small waterfall. Cool stuff. We then
moved onto the dead sea. It seems obligatory that when one goes to Masada one
also goes to float in the Dead sea. They are right next to each other, and if
you buy enough Aveda skin care products at the base of Masada you are granted
free entrance to a little spa + dead sea resort. We did this, taking the
opportunity to buy gifts for our parents. The resort was packed with
exclusively birthright attendees, most of which were probably of the age group
18-22. Hillel also leads birthright trips, and shared with us earlier that he
isn't too fond of that age group (apparently most American 18-year-olds want to
drink more than learn about Israel, go figure). We followed along with the
hordes of birthrighters and floated in the dead sea, doused ourselves in mud,
floated again, and changed and left. It was very touristy and crowded and weird
being with young birthrighters, but it was something we were obligated to do.
Also, actually being in the dead sea was surreal. It has around a 33% salt
content, which makes you unexpectedly buoyant. I felt like a wine cork bobbing
around in normal water; it would've been hard to submerge your entire body
(although you wouldn't want to, because the salty water burns your eyes).
Around 3 in the afternoon, we started to make our way back towards Jerusalem.
We stopped at the Jordan river in hopes of witnessing baptisms (people believe
Jesus was baptized there), but we just missed a tour bus full of
freshly-baptized Christians. We also briefly stopped at a Bedouin outpost along
the side of the highway and took pictures. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="image"&gt;
&lt;img src="./static/images/travel/GOPR0255.JPG" width="800" /&gt;
&lt;div class="caption"&gt;Walking around in Ein Gedi&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="image"&gt;
&lt;img src="./static/images/travel/GOPR0263.JPG" width="800" /&gt;
&lt;div class="caption"&gt;Ein Gedi was a welcome oasis&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="image"&gt;
&lt;img src="./static/images/travel/GOPR0269.JPG" width="800" /&gt;
&lt;div class="caption"&gt;Floating in the dead sea&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="image"&gt;
&lt;img src="./static/images/travel/IMG_2902.JPG" width="800" /&gt;
&lt;div class="caption"&gt;Looking over the river Jordan into Jordan.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="image"&gt;
&lt;img src="./static/images/travel/IMG_2907.JPG" width="500" /&gt;
&lt;div class="caption"&gt;Pitstop at an old bedouin outpost. The stone hut
is likely a couple thousand years old.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We got back to Jerusalem and then had to bid Hillel farewell. Hillel was
by far the best person I could've imagined to introduce me to Israel. He was
instantly our friend, and we got the opportunity to discuss so much more than
just history and key points about sites of interest. I can't even begin to
describe how fantastic of a guide Hillel was, nor even enumerate the qualities
that made him so good. After saying our goodbyes, we headed out to a little
restaurant that Hillel recommended and I nearly fell asleep while eating.
Utterly exhausted, we caught a cab home and passed out immediately. &lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Israel"></category></entry></feed>